<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A faithful narrative of the life and death of that holy and laborious preacher Mr. John Machin late of Astbury in the county of Chester. With a præfatory epistle thereunto; written by that excellent person Sir Charles Wolseley Baronet. Published for the furtherance of real piety in ministers and others.</title>
            <author>Newcome, Henry, 1627-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70718</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N896</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30742</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834871</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834871</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39482</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70718)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39482)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1467:6, 1954:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A faithful narrative of the life and death of that holy and laborious preacher Mr. John Machin late of Astbury in the county of Chester. With a præfatory epistle thereunto; written by that excellent person Sir Charles Wolseley Baronet. Published for the furtherance of real piety in ministers and others.</title>
                  <author>Newcome, Henry, 1627-1695.</author>
                  <author>Wolseley, Charles, Sir, 1630?-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>prinred [sic] for Nevill Simmons at the three Crowns in Holbourn Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Henry Newcome.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads:  The life and death of Mr. John Machin.</note>
                  <note>Incorrectly identified on reel 1954 as Wing (2nd ed.) L2033.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library ("Early English books, 1641-1700" reel 1467) and Dr. Williams's Library (reel 1954).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Machin, John, 1624-1664 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39482:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39482:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Faithful NARRATIVE OF THE LIFE and DEATH OF That Holy and Laborious PREACHER Mr. <hi>JOHN MACHIN,</hi> Late of <hi>Aſtbury</hi> in the County of <hi>Chester.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a Praefatory Epiſtle there unto; Written by that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Perſon Sir <hi>Charles Wolſeley</hi> Baronet.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the furtherance of Real Piety in Miniſters and others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Prinred for <hi>Nevill Simmons</hi> at the three Crowns at <hi>Holbourn Conduit.</hi> 1671.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:39482:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39482:2"/>
            <head>A PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ractical Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is the great End of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on while we live here; he that attains fartheſt therein, will be found wiſeſt to himſelf, and moſt beneficial to others: 'Tis
<pb facs="tcp:39482:3"/>
much in Divinity, as 'tis in Philoſophy, where the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice augments the Science above all bare Theories, and renders it moſt uſeful and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible to Mankind. When men confine Religion to Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, they turn <hi>Divinity</hi> into <hi>Metaphyſicks,</hi> where they diſpute and divide with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out End: to reduce it to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, is to purſue its proper tendency, and to make it (as indeed it is) the great Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Peace. This enſuing Diſcourſe is not a little ſubſervient to that Highest End of Religion; being in its own Nature, an
<pb facs="tcp:39482:3"/>
earneſt perſwaſive to a ſerious Practice of Holineſs, by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting before us the Example of one ſingularly Eminent therein. The Lives of Holy Men teach us what ought to be done, and at once convince us that it may be done; they ſuperſede all thoſe lazy excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, men are too apt to make about the practicability of what God requires, and give us the most taking proſpect of the Eaſe and Excellency of all Christian Duties in the Beauty of a Heavenly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; 'Tis to Record a great inſtruction to the World, to Write the Life of a
<pb facs="tcp:39482:4"/>
good man, and he's a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Benefactor to Religion that Reſcues ſuch a Treaſure from the common Conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Time, and Stores it up for Poſterity. 'Twere pitty, that what will be ever rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Heaven, ſhould be ſoon forgot upon Earth; or that the beſt Subject of Story ſhould ſilently Expire in Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion We owe no ſmall Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions both to Learning and Religion to ſuch, who have Tranſcribed the Lives of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Men, and thereby made them the Companions of every Age. No Humane Motivelike Example, nor is
<pb facs="tcp:39482:4"/>
there any Attractive to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Actions, ſo great as ſuch Actions themſelves. 'Twas the Story of <hi>Alexanders</hi> Life, that firſt inflam'd that Noble Genius of <hi>Caeſar;</hi> and 'twas the Example of ſome Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Martyrs,</hi> that first made the famous <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> a Chriſtian: St. <hi>Paul</hi> found how prevailing Example was, and therefore Preached the Goſpel from his own; thoſe things, ſays he to the <hi>Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians, which you have heard and ſeen in me, do.</hi> God himſelf eminently commends to us this way of improving the World, by propoſing the
<pb facs="tcp:39482:5"/>
best Patterns, ſince ſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable a part of the Bible, is a Sacred Regiſter of Holy Mens Lives, and one whole Book, that of the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> ſeems chiefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, to conveigh to us the Hiſtory of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Life after his Converſion.</p>
            <p>This following Collection may modestly expect a fair Reception from all hands: he must be a Reader very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to Religion and himſelf, that diſlikes the Revival of ſuch a Holy Mans Life; in which there is no real Offence given, either to the Jew, or to the Gentile, or to the
<pb facs="tcp:39482:5"/>
Church of God. Such a man as lived and dyed free from all corrupt and unſound Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; one who in the courſe of his Ministry, never ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticated the Goſpel with any fancifull Speculations; one wholly untainted with the least Faction or contempt of Authority; one that lived not in the impalement of any Party. In ſhort, a man of a Catholick Spirit, who made Religion his Buſineſs, and Travelled with the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Mankind. A wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Pattern both as a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and a Christian; in either capacity, the beſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb facs="tcp:39482:6"/>
I can give the Reader, is in the Words of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour upon another occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Go and do thou like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ch. Wolſeley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:39482:6"/>
            <head>The Life and Death of that Holy <hi>Man of God,</hi> and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious Preacher, Mr. <hi>John Machin</hi> late of <hi>Aſtbury.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>R. <hi>John Machin,</hi> was Son to <hi>John Machin</hi> of <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> near <hi>New-caſtle</hi> in the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of <hi>Stafford.</hi> His Mother <hi>Katharine</hi> was of the <hi>Vernons</hi> of <hi>Audley</hi> in the ſame <hi>County.</hi> His Father was a <hi>Yeoman</hi> of good Eſtate, an antient Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder; that Eſtate of <hi>Seabridge</hi> having continued in the Name of the <hi>Machins</hi> from the 23 <hi>Hen.</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:39482:7"/>
8. (as <hi>this precious Servant of God</hi> hath himſelf computed out of his antient Deeds) and he finds himſelf the <hi>ſeventh</hi> Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Name that have Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited that eſtate. And what a pious improvement he makes of that <hi>Obſervation,</hi> we ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in its due place.</p>
            <p>He was born at <hi>Seabridge, October</hi> 2. 1624. and baptized the ſame day at <hi>Newcaſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was the only Son of his ſaid Parents, and therefore care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully brought up by them in his Youth at the beſt Schools that were near, eſpecially with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Mr. <hi>Orme</hi> at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> and that famous Mr. <hi>John Ball</hi> at <hi>Whitmore,</hi> who brought up ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Youths in School-learning, together with his own Sons.</p>
            <p>He was ſometimes intended for the <hi>Inns of Court,</hi> but his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:39482:7"/>
tenderneſs of him, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs to part from him, is ſuppoſed to be the greateſt hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance of that deſign. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon being taken from School he was imployed in husbandry for ſome years, and other youthful recreations, as ſome well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and often did recount with admiration, when they ſaw him afterwards ſo highly ingaged in the exerciſe of the Law of God, day and night.</p>
            <p>In particular he was addicted to cock-fights, which made him ſay thus (in ſome <hi>Memorials</hi> that he left off himſelf and family for the uſe of his ſonne) <q>Twenty years did I live the Devils bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave, which is time loſt, and not <hi>Living</hi> in a good ſence, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3.</q> And hath often ſaid to ſome of his dear friends when they have been walking with
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39482:8"/>
him in ſome of the wayes at <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, O with what an heartfull of vanity have I in dayes paſt gone this way?</hi> And at other times, <hi>This way have I followed ſin where now I follow Chriſt; I am now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going, and un-ravelling my ſinful journeys: but I that have tried both, find theſe the better wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was very prone to hearken to any motion of marriage made unto him, though not then clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with any; one at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ttoxeter</hi> he was neareſt to a concluſion with, who dyed in the mean time, which was ſome occaſion of his going to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the occaſion of the nameing of his firſt child <hi>Samuel,</hi> he ſaith thus, <hi>I was the rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to give him that name, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſhould have been mine own by right, as my Father hath told me, eſpecially ſince I came from Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge:</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:39482:8"/>
for ſaid he, <q>I beg'd thee of God in thy Mothers ſtraits, and promiſed thee to the Lord, as <hi>Hannah</hi> did her Son <hi>Samuel;</hi> but having quite forgotten my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, or not thinking at all of the way wherein God intended thee for himſelfe, I intended thee for a Husbandman, until God fetch'd thee from me into the way of the Miniſtry, which was after ſome improbabilities, and beſides the thoughts of all Friends. God had another plough for thee to follow, and another match to make, than that which I and my Friends had thoughts of.</q>
            </p>
            <p>His Father was induced by the advice of a Friend to let him goe to <hi>Cambridge</hi> for a quarter of an year, ſcarce intending him to be admitted, but to abide there for ſome ſhort time for further breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And he gladly accepted the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39482:9"/>
Motion, and went thither in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> 1645. and finding ſome kinred and acquaintance there, he was admitted in <hi>Jeſus</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>The firſt year it pleaſed God to make a gracious change in him, of which, he ſaith himſelfe, <hi>The time of my converſion was in the twenty firſt year of my age (as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) the place was</hi> Jeſus <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in</hi> Cambridge. <hi>The Texts that most overturned me were Epheſ.</hi> 6.12, 13, 14. <hi>and</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22. <hi>the one by Dr.</hi> Hill, <hi>the other by a Stranger.</hi> He often ſhew'd ſome of his acquaintance the ſeat in which he was firſt wrought upon, and told them how dearly he loved the ſight of it, and that ever after he choſe to ſit in that ſeat rather than in any other, if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to crowd into it. One evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence among many others of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39482:9"/>
eminent ſucceſs which God gave to the faithful plain preaching of that Holy man D. <hi>Hill,</hi> who went over that whole Epiſtle to the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians</hi> in a Lecture every Lords-day in the morning at ſix of the clock, which he continued for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral years. Learned D. <hi>Arrowſmith</hi> alſo about the ſame time preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over a ſuccinct body of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in <hi>Aphoriſmes</hi> in St. <hi>Iohns</hi> Colledge in the evening of the Lords-day (part whereof is ſince publiſhed) of which he hath often ſaid, that he found his heart ſo moulded to the truths de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd upon the hearing thereof, that it was greatly to his ſpiritual joy and ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>No ſooner did he find this change in his own heart, but his Friends at <hi>Seabridge</hi> found it in his letters, which ſpake the new frame of his ſoul, and were moſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39482:10"/>
inſtant pathetical perſwaſions to his Father and Mother and Siſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to look after their ſoules, and to minde the things of Eternity, which he ſeconded afterward with his holy and exemplary ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety with them, ſo that he was an inſtrument to convert all his three Siſters early unto God, and to prevaile very hopefully with his Parents in like manner, as appeared afterwards.</p>
            <p>He ſo followed his ſtudies in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> that being of ripe years, very good natural parts, and religiouſly making conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his time, he made good progreſs therein, and was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to any in the <hi>Colledge</hi> of his year, in Univerſity-learning when he left it. And though he made no <hi>Shew</hi> of learning (as ſome did) in his preaching, yet he made good <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of it, and well
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39482:10"/>
underſtood the neceſſity of it for his work.</p>
            <p>About the time of his great Grandfathers death which was in <hi>March</hi> 1647. he was ſick of a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſpotted-feaver at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> and that unto death, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and moſt about him conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which he thus mentions; <hi>That it was in</hi> Jeſus-Colledge <hi>in a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle chamber next to the</hi> Chappel <hi>on the right hand; but</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>God having ſome work for me to do had mercy on me,</hi> Phil. 2.27. <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved me, and brought me back again to ſay,</hi> Pſal. 56.13. <hi>for thou haſt delivered my ſoul from death; wilt thou not deliver my feet from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that I may walk before God in the land of the living? And</hi> Pſal. 118.17, 18. <hi>I ſhall not dye but live: and declare the works of the Lord. The Lord hath chastned me ſore, but he hath not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39482:11"/>
given me over unto death.</hi> In this ſickneſs the Lord dealt moſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully with his ſoul, planting therein great and firme reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſerving his God eminently upon Recovery, which by his grace he afterward faithfully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. And hereupon he began a <hi>Meeting of Scholars</hi> for religious ends, which continued in the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for ſeveral years after his departure, to the reſtrayning (at leaſt) of ſome, and the great ſpiritual advantage of many young Scholars there; which he managed with ſuch caution, as they might not eaſily become nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of faction, or falſe doctrine, whatever the ignorance, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of ſenſeleſs frothy perſons did ſlanderouſly vent to the contrary. Take a further account of him, and of his uſefulneſs in the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in theſe few clauſes of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39482:11"/>
letters to him from ſome Worthy Members of that Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety—</p>
            <p>
               <q>Dear Friend, I received your loving Letter, which breathed nothing but piety and good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. The next Companion to him who is both <hi>Fundator, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius, &amp; Praeſes</hi> of the Colledge of Graces, and comforts of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, is he whom God hath warmed with the ſame prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to be inſtrumental for the inlivening them in others— I bleſs God, the ſociety you were the founder of in the Colledge, do grow <hi>numero</hi> et <hi>menſura</hi>— And you have here my real thanks, in that you have been inſtrumental in ſetting religious meetings on foot, wherein you reap much of the anſwer of your prayers, in that they carry it ſo prudently yet, as I hear of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39482:12"/>
nothing but what malice and guilt tax them withal— In all my ſerious thoughts I ſee you repreſented to me, either as a <hi>pattern</hi> of ſtrict walking, or an <hi>upbraiding</hi> of my little ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs, but alwayes a <hi>bleſsing</hi> and a <hi>comfort</hi> in this, that I have known you, and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of your life, and that I reap the benefit of your prayers and beſt affections, which is a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure I alwayes deſire to prize above all the Jewels in the world, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And from another eminent Perſon: My Dear and Precious Friend, I received yours— your lines ſweetly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh me. O that I could hear oftner from you. It glads my ſoul to ſee your conſtancy. O that your example might be a motive and incentive to me, to be more ſteady ſettled and fixt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39482:12"/>
upon God, in the way of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Theſe are but a taſt of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny letters from <hi>Cambridge,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſeveral do bleſs the Lord that ever they ſaw his face.</p>
            <p>But his Activity in Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice was not a little diſturbed by the malice of Satan, who fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently after his recovery from ſickneſs, annoyed and tormented him dreadfully in his <hi>Dreames</hi> (which greatly confirmed him in his chriſtian zeale) ſo that he hath often immediately upon waking run in his waſtcoat into his Study, and betaken himſelf to his earneſt prayers againſt that miſcheivous Fiend.</p>
            <p>He Commenced <hi>Batchelor in Arts, Anno</hi> 1649. and after his Commencement came into the Countrey; and ſpent part of the year among his Friends, and in viſiting ſome neighbouring Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39482:13"/>
that were deſtitute, with his pains.</p>
            <p>He was Ordeined <hi>Minister</hi> at <hi>Whitchurch, Feb.</hi> 20. 1649. In which ſervice he ingaged before hand all the prayers he was able to muſter up, not only of friends near at hand, but ſome ſcores of miles diſtant for a bleſſing upon that Ordinance; and when we conſider how pathetically he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged them, (thus in one Epiſtle, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the</hi> 20th <hi>of February, Pray and prevaile for us,</hi>) what a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of prayers there was in ſeveral places on that day, and the rich crop and harveſt reaped after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; we think it worthy the reflection of thoſe <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who never wonne a ſoule to Chriſt, from what principle, in what manner, and for what ends, they firſt ingaged in this ſacred Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:39482:13"/>Though he was not at preſent diſpoeſd to ſettle at any place, yet he was loath to go about his work without Ordination; and that which induced him to continue unfixed for a ſpace, was his large deſire after ſoules, not only of his friends and kindred, but of all his neighbours, as far as he could ſee, or know, or goe; he even travelled in birth for ſuch as had not ſeen his face, <hi>that Chriſt might be formed in them.</hi> And the largeneſs of his heart herein, was frequently expreſſed in his moſt earneſt prayers unto God, for the inlarging of his Kingdome, in Families, Towns, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; which he would name with the greateſt affection both in his prayers and letters, crying out, O that whole <hi>Staffordſhire</hi> and <hi>Cheſhire</hi> might be ſaved!</p>
            <p>And by this time he had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39482:14"/>
and intimacy with all that were eminent for Piety in all the parts adjacent, and greatly did he ſtirre up the grace of God in them. And he was extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily qualified and prepared by the Lord for this work, in an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecial juncture of time, the heat of controverſies mannaged by Sword Pen and Pulpit, having ſadly prevailed to the juſtling out the lively ſenſe of the main things wherein all were agreed. And divers Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters were ſo taken off theſe great matters by other work which the Enemy had found them, (the tares he had ſown in the fiield) that to preach of <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> &amp; <hi>Converſion,</hi> were almoſt new things to many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And this good man was ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly fitted to retrieve the Great work back again into the hearts
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:39482:14"/>
and hands of his <hi>Brethren;</hi> having never intermedled with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies either in <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> but ſetting out with all his might upon the main things, and dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving on the work of converſion where-ever he came.</p>
            <p>And his ſucceſs was great: In his Fathers houſe at <hi>Seabridge</hi> the Lord made him eminently inſtrumental for his three Siſters converſion: His Parents great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly favoured the wayes of God, much furthered him in his work, and were cheerful entertainers of well-diſpoſed people upon ſolemn occaſions. And there was ſuch an habituated courſe of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious converſe ſet up in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, by his ſtaying there the <hi>firſt</hi> year, that an eminent <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister</hi> at his firſt coming thither, and beholding their order, zeal, and forwardneſs in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> could
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39482:15"/>
not forbear, inſiſting the next day on thoſe words of <hi>Moſes, Numb.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Envieſt thou for my ſake?</hi> being the reſult of that dealing he was forc'd to, with his own heart upon that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And this Ointment on <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> head ran down to the skirts of his Cloathing, for he was a precious ſavour to the very poor ſervants of the houſe, with whom he was unweariedly importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to be holy, and prevailed much. A notable pledge of the future ſucceſs of his <hi>Miniſtry</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on others.</p>
            <p>In reference hereunto, he takes occaſion himſelfe to ſay thus of his Father; <hi>My Father</hi> John Machin <hi>did more for our family than his progenitors, building both Houſe and Barns from the ground,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But moſt of all he may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, for bringing up me his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39482:15"/>
Son to, and at the</hi> Univerſity, <hi>who was (through Grace) inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to bring the Goſpel in its power into our Family, which was more glory to the ſame, than if the materials of the houſe had been all turned into pure Gold, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of let thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> (upon the Chimney-ſtone in the Parlour) <hi>be witneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.15— 22. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.7— 42. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.18— 25. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.10— 20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.1.12— 19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.17. <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.10. <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.21. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 48.35. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.12 <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.14, 15, &amp; 20.24. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.34. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9.</note> 
               <hi>when it may be ſaid, bleſsed be he, and they, who brought His Name hither to record it. To God aolne be the whole Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His uſual way after preaching was to repeat, and to aſſemble to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as many as he could to the place where he lodged, and there to ſpend as much time as he was
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39482:16"/>
able, in preſſing things further upon them, and in holy and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent diſcourſe, with unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able heat and vigour; which made one of his Kinred ſay, that he liked his Couſen <hi>Machin</hi> well, but that he made his houſe a <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel</hi> when he came to him.</p>
            <p>And during this time he was unfixed, as he expreſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a <hi>Letter</hi> to a Friend of his in <hi>Cambridge; I am yet placeleſs, Charities ſervant, deſired to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places, but in part reſolved to fix at</hi> Ashburne, <hi>for every other Sabbath, reſerving the other for the ſervice of Neceſsity and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which may be found in theſe parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And accordingly he did, as himſelf records. <hi>At the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of</hi> An. 1650. <hi>I was called co</hi> Aſhburne <hi>in</hi> Derbyſhire, <hi>where God was with me two years, and though my labours were not in that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39482:16"/>
Towne ſo ſucceſsful as I deſired, yet I had Gods preſence much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting my ſoule, and the ſoules of many Christian friends thereabout.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About this time he was with a <hi>Quaker</hi> on his death-bed, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after the firſt ſpringing of that <hi>Sect</hi> in <hi>Staffordſhire,</hi> and the more earneſtly he prayed with the ſick perſon, the more raging he was; which was an argument to him, as alſo to ſeveral of the company then preſent, that <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keriſme</hi> was a degree of <hi>Poſseſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whiſt he was at <hi>Aſhburne,</hi> he was a laborious preacher, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uſeful, and his ſpare dayes he laid out to the utmoſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Goſpel, by forecaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heavenly work in the <hi>More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> and darke corners of <hi>Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſhire,</hi> where the power of the Goſpel had ſcarce ever come before: ſo that he might truly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:39482:17"/>
ſay, that he gloried not in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans line, he ſowed where few had effectually ſowed before, nor then, ſave by his procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. There was no man like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded in the parts he lived in, that did ſo naturally care for the ſtate of ſoules, for indeed he ſought not <hi>his own,</hi> but the <hi>things of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> He would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with his Brethren, that were intimate with him, and knew the ſincerity of his heart, and deſign herein, to meet him in thoſe parts, and to preach at ſeveral places neer together, ſometimes <hi>three</hi> or <hi>four</hi> dayes together. And the people were ordinarily ſo far made willing, that they would flock (to his great joy) from place to place after the means of Grace; and he had the comfortable teſtimony of Gods approving his wrok, in the good that many ſoules received thereby.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:39482:17"/>Take a taſte of his heavenly ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in a <hi>Letter</hi> of his ſent to a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> wife, that thought her husband long from her, then with him in the Lords Worke— <hi>July</hi> 9. 1652.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Dear Friend,</hi> I do heartily bleſs our God for what he hath done for you, and eſpecially for your ſoule; I pray believe, you heard theſe following words as coming out of the mouth that firſt ſpake them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.14. And ſay in faith, as you may in his own language, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138.8. It is to me a great ſign of what the Lord hath done for you, that you are ſo willing to part with your (I know) dear Husband for the Lords ſake, and his works ſake, but <hi>He</hi> is, and <hi>It</hi> is worthy. Think ſtill it is to the Lord, and ſhould a Husband be between
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39482:18"/>
a gracious heart and Chriſt our Lord? God forbid we ſhould think ſo, who have had already in hand for every ſtep word and thought for him, from him more weight and worth, than a wedge of <hi>Ophirs</hi> Gold, beſides thoſe thouſands of years in glory that are yet in rever<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion— and wherein I cannot thank you or him, my Lord ſhall, my Lord ſhall, my Lord ſhall; elſe his word failes and Ile com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.9.</q>
            </p>
            <p>After two years ſpent at <hi>Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne</hi> he ſayes, he ſaw nothing to contradict his reſolutions to part from them, and that the Lord cut out work for him elſewherere, judging his reaſons ſufficient for removal, he proceeds— <hi>I was called thence to</hi> Atherſton <hi>in</hi> War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wickſhhire, <hi>where I ſpent one year
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39482:18"/>
in a</hi> Lecturers <hi>place, and the Lord did abundantly crown my poor pains on a ſudden with converſion-work, which made me ſay,</hi> Cant. 6.12. <hi>Or ever I was aware, my ſoule made me like the</hi> Chariots <hi>of</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minadib. <hi>But I ſaw not the Lords mind and will to continue me there, in which I ſaw the Lords hand, and for the time was content, for I wanted nothing, having a</hi> Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge-home <hi>for ſupply: And I had my hearts deſire in opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to extend my labours to</hi> Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſhire, <hi>and otherwiſe ſome Lords-dayes, and many week-dayes, no one gainſaying; which I ſaw was for the deſtruction of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils work, and an aking-tooth he carried againſt me, but two things ſtay'd my thoughts in my travels from place to place, and houſe to houſe: My Saviours leading the way,</hi> Acts 10.38. <hi>And
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39482:19"/>
this; The more the Devil hates me, the more my God loves me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This year was his time to have Commenced <hi>Mr. in Arts,</hi> which he inclined to doe, chiefly to give teſtimony of his reſpect to <hi>Learning,</hi> and the <hi>Schools</hi> thereof, in a time when too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were bent againſt them; but his Eſtate being enough to make him a <hi>Compounder,</hi> whereby ſome extraordinary charges would be expected from him more than he could well ſpare, he ſate down with this conſideration, that he thought he might lay out that money more to the <hi>Honour of the Goſpel,</hi> than to part with it for the <hi>Honour of a Degree,</hi> though the ſingle charge he could wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly have born upon the other account.</p>
            <p>His removal thence to <hi>Aſtbury</hi> he thus records himſelf: <q>I was
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39482:19"/>
ordered and called to <hi>Astbury</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> about <hi>Novem.</hi> 17. 1652. but expreſt not my full conſent until the Spring fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing— Then I left <hi>Atherſton.</hi>
               </q> About this time his Father dyed, of which he ſaith thus, <q>He dyed on <hi>March</hi> 12. 1652. being the Sabbath day about ten of the clock at night, about the 55th year of his Age, with theſe words in his mouth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.5. Behold thou haſt made my days as an hand breadth, and mine age is as nothing before thee; Verily every man at his beſt ſtate is altogether vanity.</q> And ſaid to his Mother and Siſters ſtanding by &amp; weeping; <q>why do you ſo? you have a God that will be better than ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Husbands and Fathers.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He wiſely obſerved, when ſuch an unthought of loſs befel
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:39482:20"/>
him, how he was imployed at that inſtant— ſaying. <hi>At the time he dyed I was at prayer, and that with the moſt remarkable impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that I ever had, both in plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for mercy for him, and on a ſudden ſubmitted to the Lords de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination.</hi> Many obſervable warnings he had from the Lord of this Event, before it came to paſs; His ſerious and ſolemn ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and application of <hi>Job</hi> 21.23, 24. in the Family, before any ſickneſs appeared, <hi>March</hi> 9.2. His earneſtneſs to know his Fathers Soul-eſtate, before they parted the next morning, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to thank his love and care in his behalfe, and to underſtand his mind and will concerning himſelf and outward eſtate, while he yet continued in perfect health. 3. The day following (having occaſion to ſend home)
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:39482:20"/>
he recommended by the meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that Scripture, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.1, 2, 3. to his Father. Theſe with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other notable paſſages, and pious improvements he made hereof, gave him hope that this ſad providence was in love to him, and in mercy to his Father, whom he could not reach to ſee in the land of the living.</p>
            <p>Not long after he removed to <hi>Astbury,</hi> and changed his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, whereof he ſaith thus himſelf, <q>The good hand of my everliving Father ſo diſpoſing, I had ſome Chriſtian acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in <hi>Darbyſhire,</hi> eſpecially I obſerved one forward in the Profeſſion at <hi>Mickleover</hi> neer <hi>Darby,</hi> who might be to me as <hi>Rebecca</hi> to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> by name <hi>Jane Butler</hi> (Daughter to <hi>John Butler</hi>) on whom my thoughts much ſetled, with ſubmiſſion
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:39482:21"/>
to my heavenly Fathers will, and ſhe became my Wife <hi>Sept.</hi> 29. 1653. at <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ttoxeter,</hi> whom God gave to me, and with her what I expected in an humble and gracious woman, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.11, 12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 29.30, 31. her price was above Rubies, her Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of outward Eſtate very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable.</q>
            </p>
            <p>His managing that affaire was in ſuch an holy and heavenly manner, that all their meetings on that account were improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the utmoſt advantage of both their ſoules, and their very marriage fixt on one of his <hi>Lect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure-dayes,</hi> where two of his <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> preached and joyn'd in the Solemnization thereof; and after two dayes ſtay with his Wife, went a long journey to the work of the Lord for many dayes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing; whereby he made it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:39482:21"/>
how much the greateſt worldly comforts were made ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate to the joy of the Lord, and wore ſo far from hindring, that they rather inlarged and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him up in the wayes of God.</p>
            <p>His firſt contrivance of a <hi>Lect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure</hi> was ſome moneths before his Fathers death, and no ſooner was the Eſtate his own, but he reſolves a ſhare of it for God, and will not ſerve the Lord with that which coſts him nothing. Take his intentions in his own words, out of his own papers thus. <q>I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a monethly <hi>Lecture</hi> to be preached at theſe following towns of greateſt concourſe, <hi>viZ. Newcaſtle, Leeke, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ttoxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Lichfield, Tamworth, Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, Wolverhampton, Penkridge, Stafford, Eccleſhall, Stone, Muckleſton</hi> in the County of <hi>Stafford</hi> the laſt <hi>Friday</hi> in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:39482:22"/>
each month, allowing (of the Lords fulneſs in my hands) <hi>thirteen ſhillings</hi> and <hi>four pence</hi> to the Miniſters that preach to convert ſoules, and one <hi>Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> to be given to twelve of the pooreſt people in the Church. In all <hi>Eight pounds and twelve ſhillings</hi> in the year. This was the reſolution of an heart ingaged to him, one that would honour the Lord with his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, &amp; is <hi>J.M. July</hi> 31. 1652.</q> And preſently after his Fathers Burial, he wrote this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Paper</hi> about this thing. <q>I believed the Lord could give more dayes, but yet do will, that 8 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> 12 <hi>
                     <abbr>s.</abbr> per Annum,</hi> be for ever ſet apart for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, of my own eſtate, that immortal ſouls may be won, and Gods portion in the world increaſed. To be diſpoſed as
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:39482:22"/>
aboveſaid, or as my Brethren Mr. <hi>N.</hi> and Mr. S. my dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt fellow labourers ſhall judge and find moſt abundantly, and effectually to accompliſh Chriſts ends and mine, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.1. my hearts deſire and prayer to God for <hi>Iſrael</hi> is, that they might be ſaved.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Lecture</hi> he ſet on foot this Summer. The firſt day was at <hi>Newcaſtle, Aug.</hi> 4. 1653. where his two foreſaid friends did preach, as alſo the third courſe which was at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ttoxeter Sep.</hi> 29. following, being the day of his marriage. And this buſineſs was ſo much in his heart and purpoſe, that when ſome ſcruple was made about it in the ſettlement of his Land at marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, he hath theſe words in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter— <q>Whether I change my
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:39482:23"/>
condition or not, I have cauſe and call to reſpect my promiſe to the Lord and his Goſpel, in the thing I intended; which I think will now be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the change of my condition.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And that you may diſcerne the undiſſembled holineſs of his heart, and bent of ſoule alſo to this good work, we ſhall tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe ſome paſſages of the Will he made <hi>Nov.</hi> 16. 1653. not two moneths after his marriage— <q>I commit my ſoule to God, <hi>my God</hi> and <hi>my Saviour,</hi> that created and redeemed it, even into the boſome of the Father of Spirits; my body to my Father Corruption, and to the Worms my Mother and Siſter, <hi>Job</hi> 17.14. In hopes he will make good to me (who with them ſome time have endeavoured to ſerve him) his promiſe of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:39482:23"/>
Eternal Life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.7. As for my dear beloved Wife, I freely return (and I pray it may be with advantage) to him that hath lent her, to whom I leave, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. laſt, <hi>Jude</hi> 24. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.10, 11. hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that I leave them heirs toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with me, or rather with Jeſus Chriſt, of a Kingdome that cannot be removed. If the Lord ſhould graciouſly give me Iſſue, (I pray it may be of his Heritage, and prepared for a Room in Heaven!) to it I would leave, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9. and I pray God ſee it executed according to my will. And it is my will concerning my Heir, (if the Lord give one) that he may be a <hi>Samuel</hi> lent to the Lord and his Service in the Miniſtry; for I can ſay, he is an <hi>asking of the Lord,</hi> as was
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39482:24"/>
                  <hi>Samuel.</hi> And that he may have my inheritance, perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Fathers and my will concerning my Lecture. As for my Perſonal <hi>Subſtance, &amp;c.</hi> ending thus — Praying who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever rules here, may keep open houſe for God and his, and all I leave may be his, to whom I would in faith ſay, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.5. hereunto ſubſcribing with my heart and hand, <hi>J. M.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And in a Schedule dated here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with as followeth. <hi>Some parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars concerning the thing that hath long been in my heart to do for God, written as my last will, as an occaſion of ſome ſtanding Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, when I am not.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Motives.</hi> Gods Glory, Chriſts Kingdomes increaſe, and poor Souls Salvation, an expreſſion of my thankfulneſs for what he hath done for our family, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:39482:24"/>
for me the leaſt and laſt of it. And the rather, becauſe I am here in my own apprehenſion ſo little ſerviceable in ſpeaking, doing, and ſuffering for him, and nothing at all advantageous in writing, as others have been, and I could have deſired. Thoſe <hi>Motives,</hi> together with that bleſſed experience I have had of its advantage already through Gods ſealing work with it, makes me to think my ſelf fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured the more of God, if I may do this for him; and I doubt not but he can and will, if need be, give me and mine much more than this, as is ſaid, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 52.9. and if I could ſay as <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.23. I would think it little betwixt him and me, who hath ſaid, That whoſoever ſhall give you a cup of cold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to drink in my name, becauſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:39482:25"/>
ye belong to Chriſt, verily I ſay unto you, he ſhall not loſe his reward; and my Prayer is, that thoſe that come after me (whoſe it might have been) think it's better beſtowed, than the reſt.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Thing.</hi> A double <hi>Lecture, viz.</hi> of two Sermons once a month, chiefly intending Souls Converſion.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Miniſters.</hi> The moſt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox able and powerful that can be procured for love to <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> and his Service, or the will of the dead; choſen by my Truſtees ſucceſſively.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Trustees.</hi> Four Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and four Lay-men. The Miniſters I leave in truſt, and queſtion not their faithfulneſs herein for Chriſt ſake, are my deareſt fellow-labourers in our Lords work, Mr. <hi>N.</hi> Mr. <hi>S.</hi> Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and Mr. <hi>J.</hi> with whom
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:39482:25"/>
I only leave for their direction and incouragement, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. The Laymen whom I put in joynt truſt are Mr. <hi>B.</hi> Mr. <hi>M.</hi> Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and plain-hearted <hi>T. H.</hi> all whoſe faces I hope to ſee in Heaven; with them I leave for their refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment when taking ſome ſteps about it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.39, 40.— for Eternity is the place I would be for, to which when gone, I am but a little before, and you a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle behind.</p>
            </q>
            <p>This Lecture he kept up by his conſtant coſt and care, from <hi>Aug.</hi> 4: 1653. monthly, until <hi>Jan.</hi> 2. 1659. whereof he kept an exact account in a Catalogue, wherein he took notice of the day of the month, the place, the perſons that Preached, and their Texts, ſome hints of the Congregation both number and ſeriouſneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:39482:26"/>
continued it, until the times would neither incourage nor bear it, and thereupon it not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fell, but alſo (wanting pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick liberty for ſuch an Exerciſe according to the purpoſe of his heart) he ſuſpended his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and diſpoſed this Land otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>It ſeems to be like the pious intention of <hi>David,</hi> upon the moſt holy and affectionate mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.2. (and ſuch, as we read <hi>not</hi> that <hi>Solomon</hi> had, that after did it) to build an houſe to the Lord. But the Lord accepted his deſire, bleſſed him for his pious deſign, but would have his Son do it. So God may revive this deſign on the hearts of his Son or Succeſſors, who find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the bleſſing of their Fathers Prayers, Piety, and Promiſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending upon them, may ariſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:39482:26"/>
to build and finiſh what he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan.</p>
            <p>We find him now ſetled at <hi>Aſtbury,</hi> whether he came to keep houſe in <hi>May</hi> 1654. where he ſaith himſelf,—<hi>I was entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without exception or interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And though for ſome years we met with troubles, yet did the Lord ſtand betwixt me and all my trouble, ſo that many times I was as a man wholly free, and was made amends for all my Sufferings of that nature, by the Lords pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, ſweet and powerful in his Ordinances, eſpecially in that of the Lords Supper, there ſet on foot in</hi> March 1654. <hi>and continued without interruption monthly, or once in ſix weeks till Anno</hi> 1660.</p>
            <p>And the Lord did mightily ſtrengthen his hands and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage his heart in this ordinance, and great care he took in prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:39482:27"/>
for it, ſpending the Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day before the <hi>Sacrament</hi> in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick prayers and preaching Gods Word, and the day after the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> in thankſgiving at his own or ſome other neighbour-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, eſpecially where there fell out in any Communicants fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly any occaſion of ſpecial thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, as recovery from ſickneſs or the like.</p>
            <p>A faithful account he hath taken and left hereof, noting the Text preached upon, by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or his Brethren on thoſe dayes, and according to his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation giving a general cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of Gods dealing with them in his Ordinance in ſuch words as theſe: <hi>The Lords ſupper was</hi> Sep. 21. 1656. <hi>a day of breaking bread indeed, for Chriſt was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the breaking of ſome hearts, that thought they could never be
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:39482:27"/>
broken.— The Thanksgiving was at— whereby many it was ſaid,</hi> Pſal. 103. 1 Sam. 7.20. Again, <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p.</hi> 1660. His laſt <hi>Sacrament</hi> there thus— <hi>A good and great day as formerly, the Lords preſence and Communion with his Blood made it ſo. And as much cauſe of thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving for all the Ordinances that day: eſpecially I,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By Mr. <hi>Ms.</hi> coming to <hi>Ast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> he had only opportunity of preaching there each other Lords day, and had liberty on the other for his <hi>Charity-ſervice,</hi> which he heartily rejoyced in, and was ready freely to help any of his Brethren, ſo that he was ſeldome a day at eaſe. And now he had opportunity to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Miniſters and Congregations in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> where the Lord bleſſed his indeavours to many ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:39482:28"/>For his labours here were much inlarged by the many <hi>Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes</hi> which he kept upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions offered, unto which he was very ready, and would ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up ſuch ſpecial things as any in or out of his family deſired to be recommended unto God in prayer on ſuch days, and at other times, and preſs them to particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize ſome ſpecial thing, leſt they ſhould come unto God on a ſleeveleſs errand, which things he would frequently write down in a paper for that purpoſe, that thoſe who were imployed might read it, and ſo be inabled perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently to pray for one another. And he did much deſire to make theſe dayes, and indeed all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances very ſerious, and to reſcue them from that formality that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily accompanies them, being little content with the work done,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:39482:28"/>
unleſs he found ſomething done thereby upon his own and others hearts. Great benefit and comfort he knew was to be had in theſe ordinances, and he would not reſt contentedly without it; but diligently obſerved the ſucceſs of them, and upon Gods withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from him, made it his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſeek his God untill he found him again, and the <hi>Cauſe</hi> alſo of his withdrawing.</p>
            <p>The ſtrength of affection which he had in Gods worſhip was diſcernable to all that joyned with him, ſo that he ſeem'd <hi>Deum toto ictu animae tetigiſſe,</hi> and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in <hi>ſinging of Pſalms,</hi> which he did with ſuch an appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent intention of mind and heart as is not ordinary, and divers yet living ſhal never forget with what faith and fervency he would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce <hi>Amen, Amen,</hi> at the end of a prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:39482:29"/>And after holy duties his heart was (commonly) greatly lifted up in the wayes of the Lord, and though he far'd never ſo well in it, yet he had not done with an Ordinance when it was over, but had the <hi>heart</hi> unto, and the <hi>art</hi> of improving an inlarged heart and would then with a Dexterity and Sincerity of his own put on to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcourſe; as not only publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly urging things <hi>pro forma,</hi> but would follow it after with all his might, as if (being the Lords Embaſſador) he waited for an anſwer to him that had ſent him.</p>
            <p>A moſt unwearied man he was in Religious Duties, and was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver obſerved to give our, though ſometimes on ſpecial occaſions they continued all night therein. After one of theſe dayes of ſpecial Communion with God, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:39482:29"/>
with two or three beloved friends in private, and there moved each of them to name ſome <hi>one thing</hi> they would chiefly deſire of the Lord, and ſo each of them pray'd over all thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars that were caſt in. And the impreſſions and affections raiſed in their hearts by this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, will not eaſily be forgotten by ſuch as yet ſurvive.</p>
            <p>And for the increaſe of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Holineſs, he held up a <hi>Conference</hi> to his own and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples great benefit, and that no time might be loſt, nor any ones Mite neglected, he would take the anſwers of thoſe that were abſent at the ſtated times, when he occaſionally and opportunely met them, and ſometimes before the whole Aſſembly were gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together at dayes of Prayer; ſo that he was alwayes doing and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:39482:30"/>
deſigning the beſt advantage of the peoples Souls upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Whilſt he was Miniſter at <hi>Aſtbury,</hi> it pleaſed the Lord to give him four of the five Children which the Lord made him Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of; concerning whoſe births he thus ſpakes in the faithful <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morials</hi> which he left. <q>The firſt Will I made was ſuddenly after Marriage <hi>[he means the firſt formed Sealed Will]</hi> and in it ſpoke of a Son <hi>Samuel,</hi> as if I had ſeen him by faith, though he was not then in being; and it was a full quarter of a year before we had ſenſible hopes of a Child, which was given us about <hi>March</hi> 9. 1653. at which time the Orchard was planting. In <hi>May</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we came to ſet up houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping at <hi>Aſtbury,</hi> where God
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:39482:30"/>
gave us the birth of our asking of God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Samuel</hi> born, <hi>Nov.</hi> 13. about eleven of Clock at night, Baptized the Sabbath day following; chiefly called <hi>Samuel,</hi> becauſe asked of God by Father, Mother, by both, and many Chriſtian friends there and elſewhere, with great ends propounded at ſuch times of Prayer, <hi>viz.</hi> that he might be one to bear Gods Name here in his Church on Earth, and one to take up a Room prepared for him in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The Lord be Surety for thee my Son! The Lord for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid thou ſhould'ſt come ſhort of theſe ends, prayed thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</q> Thus did he ſet upon his head the Remembrance of the Mercy of God in his Birth, as the Servants of God of old did make the very names of their Children,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:39482:31"/>
the means of remembring Gods ſignal mercies to them, and ſo conſtant occaſions and provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to Gods praiſe, which this gracious Man abounded in. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain—<hi>In the firſt year of his life, he was by ſickneſs twice under the ſentence of death; but Prayer that obtained him, kept him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another great <hi>Deliverance</hi> to this Child he recorded, which if it affect his heart when he is able to conſider it, as it did his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (who would make large Narratives thereof, and beg the ſerious praiſes of his friends for it with extraordinary affections) it will be of no ſmall advantage to his Soul to in dear him to the God of his life. Thus he records it— <q>
                  <hi>Memorandum,</hi> That <hi>July</hi> 10. 1656. the Lord prevented the death of my Son <hi>Samuel,</hi> which in all probability might
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:39482:31"/>
have been with my own hand, bowling a ſtone with all my might towards the Child, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſaw him before it went out of my hands or no, I know not; but its motion was direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly towards his face, coming up the ſteps in the Garden-walk, and the viſible means of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention in Gods hand was another ſtone that turn'd it out of the Path-way within a few ſteps of him. This was an awakening Providence to me and my Wife that day, and ſent us to our God on our knees, partly for Humiliation, partly for Gratulation.</q> And this ſtone he kept in his Study, and (without Superſtition) made it his remembrancer to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his thankfulneſs to God for this great Deliverance. And O that Parents would in this ſort
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:39482:32"/>
tranſmit to their Children an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Gods dealings with them, when they knew him not! what obligations would it lay upon them to love and ſerve the Lord, when grown to age and underſtanding? That the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to come might know them, even the Children that ſhould be born, who ſhould ariſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare them to their Children, <hi>That they might ſet their hope in God, and not forget the works of God, but keep his Commandements,</hi> Pſal. 78.6, 7.</p>
            <p>Of his <hi>ſecond</hi> Child he thus ſaith. <hi>My Daughter</hi> Lydia (<hi>ſo called for that good womans ſake,</hi> Acts 16.14.) <hi>was born at</hi> Aſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, March 29. 1656. <hi>and there baptized,</hi> Apr. 6. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My ſecond Son</hi> John <hi>was born</hi> Sept. 1. 1658. <hi>about ſix in the morning, at which time Mr.</hi> R.M.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:39482:32"/>
               <hi>(a dear Brother and Fellow-la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer) and</hi> J <hi>might be at Prayer for my wife, as I underſtood at my return. And he was no leſs a Son of Prayers. The Lord make him a Son of his bleſſings, taking him with the reſt into that Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant,</hi> Jerem. 32.40. John <hi>was baptized at</hi> Aſtbury, Sept. 12. <hi>when I gave him this name</hi> John, <hi>and prayed, The Lord be gracious to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our ſecond Daughter</hi> Sarah <hi>was born</hi> Octob. 8. 1660. <hi>and I bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized her at</hi> Aſtbury, Octob. 23. <hi>by the token of that word then and there,</hi> Joh. 3.5. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>When this Winter was paſt, this Holy man removed to <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, May</hi> 17. 1661. of whoſe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs there, he himſelf gives this account.— <q>After ſome time I found that God was with me in <hi>Ordinances,</hi> to make Converſion
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:39482:33"/>
work; and in <hi>Providences</hi> to prevent evils, and to reach good things to us. Let it be remembred to his praiſe, that <hi>Octob.</hi> 23. 1661. my Son <hi>John</hi> was within a ſtep of drowning, and Providence ordered me within fight at that time, though I had been from home the fortnight before. And not an hour after, my Daughter <hi>Sarah</hi> was almoſt choaked with a thread, to our great affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but we ſaw the Lords hand very notable in her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, as we had done the Spring before from ſickneſs in anſwer to Prayers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.4.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Another merciful preſervation of his Son <hi>John</hi> he ſubjoyns in theſe words: <hi>Memorandum, That our Son</hi> John <hi>had a notable eſcape and preſervation from drowning, as he and his Brother were coming
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:39482:33"/>
from School,</hi> Jun. 18. 1664. <hi>but bleſſed be God, who is preſent, when Parents are abſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here he continued labouring in the Lords Vineyard unto <hi>Aug.</hi> 24. 1662. at which time he took his Civil Death with many of his Brethren, being unſatisfied to Conform as the Act of Uniformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty then required. But no man took his Death with leſs reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon Superiours, or more grief for that affliction. But yet there he continued, labouring for the peoples advantage with all his ſtrength, and was a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar bleſſing to the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood round about, having his heart unceſſantly bent towards the good of Souls. And the Neighbouring Gentry, though of a different Perſwaſion, yet offered him not the leaſt moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his honeſt indeavours, as
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:39482:34"/>
being convinced of the Innocence and Peaceableneſs of his Spirit, and uprightneſs of his ends there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
            <p>After this his youngeſt Child was born, which he thus records; <hi>My Daughter</hi> Eſther <hi>was born,</hi> Jan. 28. 1663. <hi>and baptized at</hi> Whitley, Jan. 31. <hi>and called</hi> Eſther, <hi>becauſe hidden. Hidden, as to Conception until time of life; and hid, as to the time of Travel. It was then prayed, Lord give her the hid treaſure of his fear,</hi> Iſa. 33.6. <hi>and make her a hid treaſure to his houſe and ours alſo!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And having thus made uſe of theſe his <hi>Memorials,</hi> we ſhall add what himſelf ſaid of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of them in theſe words; <q>The occaſion of making and writing this Book, was a thought I had, what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of all my Fore-fathers,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:39482:34"/>
and what price I ſhould ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one of their Manuſcripts concerning the State of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, Nation or Church of God in it 500 years ſince. Whereupon I reſolved this Work for my Sons ſake, and Poſterities imitation; when it may be ſaid of us in this Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as of <hi>Iſrael</hi> once, in that <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.6. <hi>And</hi> Joſeph <hi>dyed and all his Brethren, and all that Generation.</hi> I <hi>John Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin,</hi> called by him who ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated me from the Womb, (<hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15.) to the hope of having my name in the Book of Life, and likewiſe to be an Embaſſador of my Lord Chriſt Jeſus, was in my great Maſters work at <hi>Aſtbury</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire, Anno</hi> 1655. when I firſt ſet Pen hereunto.</q> And ſo he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued it, obſerving things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:39482:35"/>
towards him and his Family to the laſt year of his life, which we have made uſe of in divers places of this <hi>Narrative.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now having brought him within the view of his <hi>Fathers</hi> houſe, before we give an account of the laſt part, wherein he took poſſeſſion of his expected Crown, we ſhall give you his juſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter. 1. In his <hi>Perſonal,</hi> 2. his <hi>Relative</hi> Capacity.</p>
            <p n="1">I. In himſelf; 1, he was of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Spirit, in the ſenſe of <hi>Pro.</hi> 17.27. as diſpaſſionate as moſt we ever knew. One that lived with him for ſome time, ſayes truly of him, That he knew not that ever he ſaw him tranſported with paſſion; but angry he would be at Sin, yet ſtill exactly after his Lord and Maſters paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being grieved for the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their hearts, <hi>Mark</hi> 3.5.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:39482:35"/>
yet his Reproofs were alwayes ſo moderated with Love and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, that the Offendor could not but ſee, that he intended them for his good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He had good natural Parts, and was no Novice in all that learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which was neceſſary for his work. For though he was more abundant in publick Preaching than moſt others, which muſt needs hinder his Studies, yet what time of vacancy he had from this work, he diligently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed for his Book, and took in <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> the <hi>Tongues, Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Poſitive</hi> and <hi>Practical Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> in his courſe of Study; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing never well, unleſs in Study, or in immediate Duties, or holy Conference: though (as it was once ſaid of <hi>Plato</hi>'s Houſhold-ſtuff) it was truly ſaid of all his Studies, There was <hi>nihil in pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pam,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:39482:36"/>
omne in uſum.</hi> And like one of the Architects in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> who when the other had made an artificial diſcourſe of his skill to contrive a new building, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe that were to make their choice of them; He only ſaid, <hi>All that this man hath</hi> ſaid, <hi>I can</hi> do. So this Holy Man had the Knowledge of Doing; what others could learnedly Diſpute and Diſcourſe of, he could learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly live in every point, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Learned Preacher.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He had an extraordinary meaſure of Holineſs and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venlineſs; according to the Obſervation that a Judicious Divine long ſince made of him That he had more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary degrees of Sanctification. He was of a quick underſtanding in the fear of the Lord, and had the tongue of the learned to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:39482:36"/>
ſpeak a word in ſeaſon to the ſtate of all Souls. This was his Maſter-piece, and was naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed to him.</p>
            <p>He had a ſingular ingenuity in improving Scripture Similitudes, and every Occurrence with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imaginable dexterity, each Tree, and Bird, and Stone, would be a Text whereon he would aptly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large; having a mighty wit for the Spiritualizing of every thing, and gathering occaſion of good Converſe in every Company, and almoſt upon every matter, and it was apparent, That out of the abundance of his heart his mouth ſpake.</p>
            <p>His holy jealouſie and fear of himſelf was very great. A dear friend that well knew him, writes thus of him. <q>Never man more watchful againſt Relapſes, nor more jealous to maintain his
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:39482:37"/>
firſt love to the height. I have ſometimes told him, that it was not uſual for Converts to retain that Land flood of comfort, that intention of zeal, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion of affection which flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in him, and was preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the height; he muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect an abatement in time, and the Current thereof to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted and ſetled in a narrower Channel.</q> He often reflected on theſe words, <hi>Ore tenus,</hi> and in his Letters intimating he was what he was heretofore, not without an admiration of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting Grace. Thereunto he aſcribed all he was. And indeed he was ſo habituated unto Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Communion with his God, that he could not patiently bear his withdrawings, and was far more ſenſibly and ſooner aware of it, than many others are, that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:39482:37"/>
can to their great loſs admit of other delights inſtead of his face and favour; but this Holy Man did moſt eagerly ſeek for him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions, till he found Him whom his Soul loved.</p>
            <p>He was a great Obſerver of the frame and bent of his heart <hi>at all times;</hi> a worthy Miniſter writes thus of him. <q>I have admired at the conſtant frame of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; he was not ſubject to that deadneſs and indiſpoſedneſs as other good men ſeem to be; his heart was continually burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with an holy zeal.</q> Take a taſt of his excellent ſweet frame of heart in this ſhort Letter-paſſage to a Friend. <hi>My dear, dear, dear Brother, I pray thee, I pray thee report the loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Lord unexpreſſible unto a poor vile empty altogether unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving worm, for I have found
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:39482:38"/>
an anſwer this day, this day more than ever to our Prayers, and can ſay, the Lords work will on, though hell ſay no: and ſtill Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, Preach, Pray and Believe,</hi> Lam. 3.25. <hi>I am conſtrained to ſay,</hi> Iſa. 63.7. <hi>Neither thou nor any of my friends can conceive how good the Lord is to me, even to me. I pray thee and others think and ſtudy how good he is to me, to me, to me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And a conſtant watch he kept over his thoughts, eſpecially of his laſt thoughts that he ſlept with, and his firſt thoughts that he waked with; and uſually they were ſome precious Scripture or other, which he would diſcourſe of to his friends with great ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity.</p>
            <p>He kept a <hi>Diary</hi> of his Life, wherein every day he wrote in Characters where he was, what
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:39482:38"/>
Scriptures he found any ſweetneſs from, what was the ſtate of his Soul towards God; and ſuch other remarkable paſſages that did occurr each day, from the year 1650. to the year he dyed.</p>
            <p>His love to the Word of God was ſuperlative: it was his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation day and night. He did conſtantly in a morning pitch up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome <hi>Verſe,</hi> which he would endeavour to infuſe into his heart; ever unwilling to leave it, till he had ſuck'd ſome virtue from it. He was chewing by Meditation the 119th. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> at the time of his ſickneſs, daily ſqueezing the virtue of one verſe thereof into his Soul, as appears by his <hi>Diary;</hi> and this he did, not formally as a task, but with that effectual ſeriouſneſs and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, that his family at home, and friends at a diſtance, in his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:39482:39"/>
Letters might perceive exactly, what dainties he had taſted. And at every vacant time, he would be looking for a word, and would find out by the caſual turning down a leaf in his Bible (which was his uſual way) ſuch paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as were very remarkable and not obſerved before. A Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thus met with, was as food to him, exceeding ſweet to his taſt, he would make much of it, and uſually would not leave it, till he had improved it to the good of others by ſpeaking or writing, that others might ſee what he ſaw, and feel what he felt in the word of God.</p>
            <p>Another uſage he had alſo, which ſhewed him to be both a good Textuary, and a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; and that was uſually to take leave with his Friends and Relations, by leaving ſome Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:39482:39"/>
with them, and thoſe moſt ſuitable to their condition; nay he hardly ſent commendations to a friend, but it was accompanied with ſome pertinent Scripture, that he ſeemed to breath no other aire but Scripture. His <hi>Bible</hi> was his conſtant Companion in the day, and uſually his Pillow at night; and many ſcores of em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatical lively expreſſions he had found therein, which the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant reading and diligence of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers could never light on. And wherever he came, he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graving ſome Scripture or other on the Mantle-poſts, and Walls, and Trees; which was ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and peculiar a courſe with him, that his acquaintance oft knew he had been in ſuch a place, by the marks he uſually left. His deſign therein being, the advantage of all mens Souls;
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:39482:40"/>
that the very novelty of ſeeing ſuch things, might ſet people up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on enquiring and looking thoſe thoſe Scriptures in their Bibles, not knowing what good one Verſe of the Scripture (thus met with) might do upon a Soul, if God ſet it on. At leaſt he found this advantage to himſelf, that when he came to a review of them, he was put in mind of that frame of heart he had when he was there before; and might taſt over again, what he had before felt, in that paſſage of the Word of God. He ſeldome wrote a Note or Letter, but he made it up with ſome ſuitable Scripture (the word of God dwelling plentifully in him) and in the <hi>Memorials</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, he inſerts Scriptures upon every occaſion, ſaying in the concluſion, <hi>The Texts of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture herein mention'd, are best
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:39482:40"/>
worth thy finding and noting in thy life, as they were in mine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His moderation was remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all ſorts of godly people, though of differing judgements; his heart and heat being wholly taken up with the great and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary parts of Religion, that all true Chriſtians agreed in: and making the ſubſtance of Religion his work and buſineſs, he never had leiſure to trouble himſelf with controverted circumſtances, nor would put his Soul out of tune with ſuch things, as had cauſed ſo much jarring and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harmony among Chriſtians. He was never (or very ſeldome, and then not out of choice) heard to diſcourſe of the dividing Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies of the times.</p>
            <p>A peculiar tryal he was exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed with, ſoon after his entrance on his Miniſterial work, and that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:39482:41"/>
was by ſtrange and horrible ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions in the night ſeaſon, as if he were cut in pieces with knives, or the like; and he was in as real agony and diſtreſs, as if he had felt the pain of ſuch tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment indeed. Perhaps it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from natural cauſes, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd by his extraordinary pains which did heat his body, and that might influence upon his fancy and diſturb it, and thereby beget ſuch apprehenſions in him. But he ſtill apprehended it to be the buffetings of Satan: they uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally followed days of great pains, and dayes of great inward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, and he was often forced by them to leap out of his bed in the night, and go to Prayer for eaſe and delivery. He would very pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetically bewayl thoſe gloomy nights, and (what cauſe ſoever they proceeded from) they were
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:39482:41"/>
great occaſions to realize the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of hell to him, and to keep him humble.</p>
            <p n="2">II. In his Relative Duties, he was abundantly diligent and faithful.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In his Family, he walked in a perfect way in the midſt of his houſe. There he conſtantly read the Scripture: a portion of the Old Teſtament in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and of the New Teſtament in the evening, and ſung ſome verſes of the Pſalms in order, at every Duty. After Reading, he examined each one preſent what they remembred and obſerved, and then would open and inlarge upon each ones portion, and alſo on what was moſt obſervable and practical in that Scripture. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did he circumſcribe Religion to Family duties (as many doe, who from morning, to evening
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:39482:42"/>
Prayer ſcarce ever think or ſpeak of ſpiritual things) but had fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarized <hi>holy Diſcourſe</hi> in his houſe all the day long, as there was any occaſion or opportunity. He alwayes repeated at home the Sermons he heard abroad. The Lords-days Sermon, he us'd to repeat the <hi>Saturday</hi> afternoon following, or ſome other Sermon to prepare for the enſuing Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath. On the Lords-day evening he would take his Children in private, and there inſtruct them, and there teach them how to pray. He conſtantly <hi>Catechiſed</hi> his Children and Servants twice in the week, cauſing them to get ſome verſes of the Scripture and of their Catechiſm daily by heart. He often had private <hi>Faſts</hi> with his family <hi>only,</hi> and was well vers'd in ſecret humiliation alſo. His ardent deſires and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:39482:42"/>
after the Salvation of his Children and other Kindred are further evident, in a ſerious <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe</hi> to his Son, on 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9. which he hath prepared; and <hi>another,</hi> which he call'd, <hi>A word to my meerly Natural Friends,</hi> on <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.7. which (if not with this Narrative) may in due time ſee the light, to the great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of his Relations and others; wherein the precious breathings of his Soul after his Children and Friends in the fleſh are largely manifeſted. And upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count he gave twenty of Mr. <hi>Baxters Calls to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconverted</hi> amongſt his Kindred and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; in divers whereof he fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and wrote ſuch pertinent <hi>Dialogues,</hi> as were moſt ſuitable to their Souls Eſtate.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In his Miniſtry indefatiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. He was in Labours oft, in
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:39482:43"/>
Journeyings oft. We may truly apply to him, that which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaid of <hi>Timothy,</hi> Phil. 2.20. <hi>We have no man like minded that doth naturally care for the State of Souls.</hi> His mighty forwardneſs and earneſtneſs in this work, his travelling, and toyling, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing all the help he could for the work, was ſo great, that it could not have been more, if he had foreſeen the ſhortneſs of his <hi>own dayes,</hi> or the length of <hi>our night.</hi> And the more univerſal was the influence of his labours, in that he was ſtrangely ſtirr'd up to Preach in ſeveral parts of the Countrey; Miniſters and people generally promoting and accepting his holy and ſincere en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, where envy or preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice did not manifeſtly interpoſe.</p>
            <p>When other Miniſters or him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf have been imployed in the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:39482:43"/>
uſual courſes of the day, he would often chooſe rather to <hi>repeat</hi> the Sermon to the people at Noon, than go to his Dinner; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the pattern of his dear Maſter before him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.33, 34. And indeed ſometimes his zeal to the work of God would carry him to do more than his body or the peoples convenience could well bear; but as it was ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meant by him, ſo it was gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally well taken by them, and God made it anſwerable in the event.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid of Mr. <hi>Latimer,</hi> that when he had reproved ſome pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant perſons in his time ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſharply, and was complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of for lack of diſcretion, he would reply, that he was glad they had no allegation againſt him, but want of diſcretion; it being evident thereby, that the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:39482:44"/>
ſubſtance of his buſineſs was right: ſo for this our glorified Brother, the worſt that could be laid to his charge was, ſometimes want of Prudence in reſpect of the length and frequency of his labours. A thing he might well be excuſed in, when ſo few tranſgreſs on that hand: many being too <hi>wiſe</hi> to be <hi>ſerious,</hi> too exact to remit the leaſt of their conceited neatneſs for the benefit of their hearers, or to go out of their rode to fetch a Soul in to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For this good Man, ſuch was his heavenly ſpirit and way in his work, that though the matter he brought was ordinary, yet the manner he delivered it in was not ordinary, and his ſucceſs was great in the Converſion of many Souls. One ſayes that well knew him, and oft accompanyed him: <hi>I cannot forget how the people after
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:39482:44"/>
a day of Preaching, would meet him with tears in their eyes, ſome fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing him, many thanking him for his pains, and by their Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances ſhewing they had met with God in the Ordinance.</hi> And this is ſure, That he that winneth Souls is truly wiſe. If that <hi>great Man</hi> on his death-bed could profeſs, that one Soul Converted by his means, would be a greater ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and comfort to him, than all the Greatneſs and Honours he had enjoyed: with what glory is this Holy Man gone off the Stage, that was an Inſtrument in the hand of Gods Spirit to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert many, and to Convince and Quicken more?</p>
            <p>His Converſe was a continual Sermon. He never went, but the Miniſter, and the warm-hearted Chriſtian went with him. He was the ſame out of the Pulpit as
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:39482:45"/>
in it. A lively Comment on the Apoſtles words, <hi>Let your Speech be alway ſeaſoned with Salt, that it may minister grace to the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers:</hi> far from that common for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality of moſt <hi>Preachers,</hi> that as if they had left all their Divinity and Heat in the Pulpit, come down and talk like other men; which tempts people to reſt little affected with thoſe Truths, that ſeem ſo little to affect the Preacher himſelf, and to hold thoſe things but meer notions, when (like the Actor of a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy that hath done his part) the Miniſter talks and walks as if he were unconcern'd in the ſolemn things he hath treated on.</p>
            <p>Some that have travelled with him a journey (which uſually were upon ſome religious account) have been even raviſhed in their ſouls with his heavenly expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:39482:45"/>
&amp; to prayer he would imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately go either publickly in the Family, or privately in his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, in every houſe where he came.</p>
            <p>He had an undaunted boldneſs in the reproving of a ſinner: How have ſome of us ſeen him in an Inne upon his journey, Thunder-ſtriking a Swearer in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>Who was it there, that durst abuſe the Name of the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?</hi> And he would ever on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, when talking with his friends on the way, chooſe ſome weighty word to ſpeak, as he met with people that paſſed by, that ſo it might ſtick, and this bread of his that was caſt on the waters, would ſome times return to him after many dayes.</p>
            <p>He had a <hi>ſingular preſence of heart</hi> and <hi>matter,</hi> to ſpeak to whomſoever he met, and great condeſcention to explain himſelf,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:39482:46"/>
wherein any did not underſtand him; as once in a Snowy day, meeting ſuddenly with a man driving his horſes, that ſaluted him, and ſaid, <hi>well met</hi> Sir; <hi>I but,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>we ſhall be better met if we meet in Heaven,</hi> and ſuch like. Few poor ever went from his door, without a moſt powerful ſpiritual almes; and he would or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them a larger allow a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, that would admit of his caeleſtial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe.</p>
            <p>But eſpecially his faculty ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled, in <hi>Diſcourſing with people on the way,</hi> with whom he would very handſomly inſinuate, into very material and yet familiar diſcourſe of Eternal things, find out their ignorance, mightily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze and convince them, and lay thereby the happy foundation of future acquaintance upon this beſt count, which practiſes of his
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:39482:46"/>
may ſhame and teach us: for alas! what through the earthlyneſs, and vanity, and what through the baſhfulneſs of our hearts, Chriſt and Heaven are generally excepted out of our diſcourſe. We can ſpeak of any thing but the ſoule, of any perſon but of Jeſus, and of any place but of Heaven; and it is almoſt a crime for a Chriſtian to talk of Chriſtiani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. What an unreaſonable thing is it, that we who pretend for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſhould not as readily, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, and cheerfully fall into diſcourſe concernig Gods word, and our Salvation, as the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and wicked ones can of their Lands and Luſts? No other talk but what leads towards God ſhall be worth talking over again in the Kingdom of Heaven. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>Dialogues</hi> that were on ſuch occaſions framed by him, are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:39482:47"/>
in the hands of friends, that would (if publiſhed) ſhew his excellent <hi>Genius</hi> this way, and perhaps ſtir us all up to be more fruitful in ſuch diſcourſe. One In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance hereof is remarkable. Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one morning to a Lecture, he met with ſome young men carrying their Cocks to a Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fight; he overtaking them, dropt this word to one of them: <hi>Friend, our Lord and Maſter Jeſus Chriſt never came into the world to ſet up ſuch ſports as theſe.</hi> Theſe words &amp; ſome further diſcourſes (though the young man went on to his ſport that day) ſtuck like an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in his liver, and he could not be at quiet, till he had learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed who this Miniſter was, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter gain'd acquaintance with him, and thereupon laid theſe and his other ſins to heart, and made an happy change of his courſes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:39482:47"/>He was a zealous improver of good ſociety. His ordinary viſits, were ſeldome finiſh'd without prayer with his friends before they parted. And when divers good people were all night together, he would be tying them as it were end to end, and engaging them to pray one after another, often to midnight, or elſe to produce their ſeveral evidences for Heaven and would ſometimes raiſe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany an hour before day in the morning to wreſtle and weepe together, that the fire might not go out upon the hearth of their ſoules being ſo conſtantly blown up; yea the very crumbs of piety that fell from him at his table, were moſt refreſhing and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and a plain argument, that it was his meat and drink to do his Fathers will and finiſh his work.</p>
            <p>He had moſt ingenious devices
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:39482:48"/>
and witty artifices, flowing from his rooted affection to God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by after ſome Solemn dayes, he would ingage his Chriſtian friends to a cloſer converſation. Take an <hi>Inſtance</hi> or two hereof, as we finde them left on record — <hi>Articles betwixt Christ and two ſoules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That we be his willing, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and obedient Spouſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That we labour by all means to know more of his mind, and then to tell it one to another, and draw to the practiſe of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That we be alwayes jealous, left each other take his room, and to be indifferent, and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in everything, and every one, but to Him and His.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That whatever creatures are betwixt us, they be improved to higheſt advantage betwixt Chriſt and our ſoules.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That we connive not at ſin
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:39482:48"/>
in each other, but be tender of one anothers ſoules and bodies.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That we love and live each day as the laſt.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That we faithfully indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour performance of each others will, while living and when dead, ſo far as Reaſon and Religion may bind.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That we be in every condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion more willing, to go live with Chriſt our Husband, than ſtay here one with another for pleaſure ſake.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That we endeavour ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nableneſs and ſuitableneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry duty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And another to this effect— <hi>Seabridge</hi> Oct. 8. <hi>where His name was that day recorded.</hi> Before the Lord &amp; in his ſtrength, I promiſe to draw neer to God, believing he will draw neer to me. I paſs away and part with my own pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:39482:49"/>
to Him, that I may be His, not anothers. Subſcribing with heart and hand, praying and believing the Lord will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take for me, that I never go back in a thought; Or elſe this will ſtand in full force againſt me at that great day to come, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13. H. N. <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.5. J. M. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.106. J. M. <hi>Zach.</hi> 8.21. M. M. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.80. N.B. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.10. E. H. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>He was one that ſet great ſtore by the prayers of his Friends, and was a very faithful remembrancer of them that deſired his prayers; which he uſed to do with that heartineſs, and ſympathy, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largedneſs of heart, that it would much work upon their hearts, and ingage them to more ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in their own buſineſs, and in affection to him, that ſo kindly concerned himſelf in their affairs.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:39482:49"/>
And with great fervour would he plead with God in their abſence, not only to ſatisfie his conſcience &amp; promiſe of remembring them, but with ſtrong cryes to prevail for them. Beſides that frequent courſe he held, of putting on perſons to tell him before prayer began, what they would have chiefly begg'd for them at the Throne of Grace, by which they were ſent into their own ſoules, to ſtudy their inward and preſent condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>A dear friend upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count ſaith thus. <q>He gave this <hi>Rule</hi> touching praying for friends, which I have, endeavoured ſince to make my directory in that Caſe. <hi>Alwayes, when you think on your Friends, let it be with a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thought.</hi>
               </q> He would ſometimes have his intimate friends write downe in his <hi>Day-book,</hi> and ſo mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:39482:50"/>
what eſpecial thing they ſhould intercede for in one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers behalf till their next meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Letters</hi> were frequent and full of Heaven, commonly ſetting time apart for writing ſuch let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as he was in arrear, and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom upon any buſineſs but Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion was interwoven; and ſuch plenty of ſweet Scriptures and poſtſcripts, that ſometimes ſome Scripture would be indorſed on the outſide of his letters, when ſent by a friends hand. In this uſeful part of <hi>Friendſhip</hi> he was abundant &amp; very profitable; there remaining yet (as is verily believed) many hundreds of his good letters in the hands of friends, wherein was ſcarce a ſyllable of any buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs but Religion. O how much good might many Able and Holy Divines do this way! to wit, by
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:39482:50"/>
ſerious letters to their Kindred, and Acquaintance, yea even to ſtrangers, which would do good not to one only, but many, yea, to the generation to come. How much doth the Church of God owe to the letters of ſome modern and primitive Divines and others? Since a great part of our <hi>New Testament</hi> is the Letters of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, the heavenly plainneſs of whoſe ſtyle this good Man did much imitate, and it is well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that the beſt part of the works of famous Writers is their Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, he was eminent in <hi>Real Charity:</hi> he had a faithful ſympathy with thoſe that were in any ſtrait and affliction, and a ready hand to help them. He was far from that clumbzy frozen and ſtrait-hearted manner of many, that are ready to ſay, <hi>go and be
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:39482:51"/>
warmed,</hi> and <hi>go and be cloathed;</hi> that are readier to cenſure their Brethrens neceſſities, and increaſe their burthens by reproaches, than to reach out their hand to their aſſiſtance. No, he was a doing Chriſtian according to, yea, and beyond his power. In his accounts to his Father from the Univerſity, they ſeldome found leſs than <hi>twelve pence</hi> a week to the poor, beſides ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>half a Crown</hi> at a time. And afterwards it was his delight to ingage others, and to contribute himſelf in a liberal manner, <hi>twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhillings,</hi> and <hi>five pound</hi> at a time to Charitable uſes; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to make a ſtock for ſuch as were poor and pious, ſometimes to help a Miniſter or other out of his ſtraits, for which the bowels of many have bleſſed God for him in divers places.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:39482:51"/>In ſhort, he was a Starr of the firſt Magnitude in the impartial judgement of thoſe that through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knew him. Thus ſaith an <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Divine</hi> to him in a familiar Letter. <hi>Dear Brother, I earneſtly deſire correſpondence with thee; Thy Letters are precious and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to my Soul; Thou art more in my heart and eye and thoughts, than all the acquaintance I have in the world; I have ſeen that in thee, that hath no little convinced me of the Reality of Religion. Theſe are not the words of a flatterer, but the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflowings of a ſincere heart,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>When we view him in his Natural and Moral accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments; in his graces, in his Relations, in his publick and private behaviour, and in his true humility and ſincerity which crowned all the reſt; we muſt needs ſay, <hi>he feared God above ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:39482:52"/>
and hath left but few ſuch Miniſters behind him.</p>
            <p>He had apprehenſions of his Death long before it came. In a Letter <hi>May</hi> 1659. concerning an <hi>Old Diſciple,</hi> this Clauſe: <hi>Will he not let me ſee him before I dye?</hi> In another <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1659. theſe words; <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 32. <hi>To which let thoughts be directed, when no more is to be ſeen or heard of me, but that I am thy Friend in ſtore, not loſt but laid up,</hi> J. M. In <hi>March</hi> 1663, he complains of frequent dejected<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and melancholy. And this paſſage he had in a letter <hi>June</hi> 28. 1664. <hi>I have been very melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome while by fits, what this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedes I know not.</hi> But the all-wiſe God, whoſe wayes are paſt find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, well knew, that the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of the Evening were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:39482:52"/>For intending ſhortly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move to <hi>Seabridge,</hi> he took in his way the houſe of a worthy <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman,</hi> and there treated on theſe words <hi>Acts</hi> 20.24. <hi>Neither count I my life dear unto my ſelf,</hi> &amp;c. which he ſtudied and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as his laſt farewel to this world in a ſickly condition, having ſpent many Sermons before on <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.3, 4, 5. ſweet preparations to life everlaſting. He grew worſe and worſe at <hi>Seabridge,</hi> and it proved an high malignant Feaver. His Wife was ſent for, who found him in his bed, and then he told her, he was ill, but whether it were life or death he would not chooſe, his Father ſhould chooſe for him. The ſeaſon for opening a vein, through the Phyſitians ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence from home, was miſt, and ſo his diſtemper prevailed. Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Face in the Glaſs, he brake
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:39482:53"/>
out very affectionately into theſe words, <hi>Ah Adam, Adam, what haſt thou done? what a beautiful happy Creature waſt thou, but now how poor and ſorrowful,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>art thou? Ah Adam, what haſt thou done?</hi> which greatly affected ſome that were preſent with him.</p>
            <p>But his diſtemper grew higher, whereby his Spirits were deadned in him, ſo that when his Wife and Children were about him, and ſhe ſaid; Love, thou ſayeſt nothing to me, nor to thy Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; he only anſwer'd, That he had ſaid to her and them too. How good therefore is it to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, what Parents and Husband ſay to us, foraſmuch as we know not, which counſel may be their laſt, and muſt ſtand for their death-bed charge unto us.</p>
            <p>On the 4th. of <hi>September,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Lords day,</hi> though through
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:39482:53"/>
his diſtemper he was ſcarce ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet perceiving it to be the Lords day, he would needs be helped up, and held up with pillows, that he might kneel down and offer at prayer, though he was diſabled from performace.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Tueſday Sept.</hi> 6. in the eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this holy Man breathed his laſt, being the 17th day of his ſickneſs, and in the 40th year of his age; and was buried <hi>Sept.</hi> 8. at <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> with a particular <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comium</hi> by the Preacher, and the profound grief of all the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. The truth is, this world was not worthy of him, ſcarce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that began no ſooner, and lived no longer, having done ſo much good in the world, as he did in his capacity.</p>
            <p>It is the ſence and character of a learned and pious <hi>Divine</hi> and at this time a <hi>Dignitary</hi> in the Church
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:39482:54"/>
—<hi>I am ſo well ſatisfied as to his extraordinary piety in the general, which I never yet heard, or believe he departed from, that I wiſh my everlasting portion may be with him</hi>— And after— <hi>To conclude, I never knew one more pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſpirited, more ſenſible of mens ſpiritual neceſſities, and more ready (to his ability) to ſupply them, more zealous for Gods glory, more delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, inceſſant, importunate, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesful in prayer, and more thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſenſible of the returns thereof, than this</hi> Holy Perſon <hi>was, of whom this degenerate world was not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, &amp; therefore having been abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in the work of the Lord, God hath ſatisfied him with never end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing experience, that his Labour (from which he now reſts) may not be in vain in the Lord.</hi> The following of whoſe example will be the beſt amends, &amp; greateſt End of writing this his Life.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:39482:54"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
